<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.39 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC8322 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="rfc7749.css"?>
<rfc docName="draft-mandm-sacm-rolie-configuration-checklist-00" category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="rolie-cc-ext">Definition of the ROLIE configuration checklist Extension</title>
    <author fullname="Stephen Banghart" initials="S.B." surname="Banghart">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
          <city>Gaithersburg</city>
          <region>Maryland</region>
          <code>20877</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>stephen.banghart@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Munyan" fullname="Bill Munyan">
      <organization>Center for Internet Security</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>31 Tech Valley Drive</street>
          <city>East Greenbush, NY</city>
          <code>12061</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bill.munyan.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Montville" fullname="Adam Montville">
      <organization>Center for Internet Security</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>31 Tech Valley Drive</street>
          <city>East Greenbush, NY</city>
          <code>12061</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>adam.w.montville@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Gabriel Alford" initials="G.A." surname="Alford">
      <organization>Red Hat, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 East Davie Street</street>
          <city>Raleigh</city>
          <region>North Carolina</region>
          <code>27601</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>galford@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2020"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <abstract>

      <t>This document extends the Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE) core
        to add the information type categories and related requirements needed to support security
        configuration checklist use cases. Additional categories, properties, and requirements based
        on content type enables a higher level of interoperability between ROLIE implementations,
        and richer metadata for ROLIE consumers. Additionally, this document discusses requirements
        and usage of other ROLIE elements in order to best syndicate security configuration
        checklists. </t>
    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t>This document defines an extension to the Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information
        Exchange (ROLIE) protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-mile-rolie"/> to support the publication of
        configuration checklist information. Many enterprises operate according to guidance provided
        to them by a control framework (<xref target="CIS_Critical_Controls"/>, <xref
          target="PCI_DSS"/>, <xref target="NIST_800-53"/> etc.), which often prescribe that an
        enterprise define a standard, security-minded configuration for each technology they
        operate. Such standard configurations are often referred to as configuration checklists.
        These configuration checklists contain a set of configuration recommendations for a given
        endpoint. A configuration recommendation prescribes expected values pertaining to one or
        more discrete endpoint attributes.</t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown
        here.</t>
      <t>The previous key words are used in this document to define the requirements for
        implementations of this specification. As a result, the key words in this document are not
        used for recommendations or requirements for the use of ROLIE.</t>
      <t>As an extension of <xref target="RFC8322"/>, this document refers to many terms defined in
        that document. In particular, the use of "Entry" and "Feed" are aligned with the definitions
        presented in section TODO of ROLIE.</t>
      <t>Several places in this document refer to the "information-type" of a Resource (Entry or
        Feed). This refers to the "term" attribute of an "atom:category" element whose scheme is
        "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type". For an Entry, this value can be inherited
        from it's containing Feed as per <xref target="RFC8322"/>.</t>

      <t>Other terminology used in this document is defined below:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Configuration Item"> Generally synonymous with endpoint attribute.</t>
          <t hangText="Configuration Checklist"> A configuration checklist is an organized
            collection of rules about a particular kind of system or platform.</t>
          <t hangText="Configuration Recommendation"> A configuration recommendation is an
            expression of the desired posture of one or more configuration items. A configuration
            recommendation generally includes the description of the recommendation, a rationale
            statement, and the expected state of collected posture information.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>TODO: There needs to be a “normative” reference to the SCAP 1.2/3 specifications and schema
        definitions</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="checklist-information-type"
      title="The “configuration-checklist” information-type">
      <t>This document registers a new information type for use in ROLIE repositories. The
        “configuration-checklist” information type represents a body of information describing a set
        of configuration recommendations. A configuration recommendation is, minimally, a single
        configuration item paired with a recommended value or range of values. Depending on the
        source, a configuration recommendation may carry with it additional information (i.e.
        description, references, rationale, etc.). Provided below is a non-exhaustive list of
        information that may be considered as components of a configuration checklist.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A “Data Stream”:</t>
          <t>A “Benchmark”</t>
          <t>A “Profile”</t>
          <t>A “Value”</t>
          <t>A “Rule” or “Group” of Rules <list style="symbols">
              <t>Description</t>
              <t>Rationale</t>
              <t>Remediation Instructions</t>
              <t>Information, described in the dialect of a supported “check system”, indicating the
                method(s) used to audit the checklist configuration item.</t>
            </list></t>
          <t>Applicable Platform Information</t>
          <t>Information regarding a set of patches to be evaluated</t>
          <t>Any supported “tailoring” information, providing a method for evaluating entities to
            refine the recommendations in the data stream without modifying the published data
            stream content. (WKM NOTE: Does “tailoring” need to be here? Why would any tailoring be
            included in a published feed? Unless the organization is re-publishing the content with
            their tailoring included.)</t>
        </list></t>

    </section>
    <section title="rolie:property Extensions" anchor="rolie-properties">

      <t>A breadth of metadata may be included with a configuration checklist as identifying
        information. A publishing organization may wish to recognize or attribute checklist authors
        or contributors, or maintain a revision/version history over time. Other metadata that may
        be included could indicate the various categories of products to which the checklist
        applies, such as Operating System, Network Device, or Application Server.</t>

      <t>This document registers several new rolie:property elements to express this metadata in a
        more efficient and automatable form.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">

          <t>contributor (0..n) <list style="symbols">
              <t>name: urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:checklist:contributor</t>

              <t> value: Indicates those individuals noted as recognized contributors to the
                configuration checklist and/or the recommendations contained within. The value MUST
                be either a plaintext name of a entity, or a link to a &lt;author&gt; element that
                describes a entity. </t>
            </list></t>

          <!-- Reformat remaining properties into the above form -->
          <t>checklist version: The <spanx style="verb">value</spanx> of the “checklist version”
            property indicates the version number of the configuration checklist, such as
            <spanx style="verb">3.1.1</spanx></t>
          <t>title: The <spanx style="verb">value</spanx> of the “title” property indicates the
            document title of the configuration checklist, such as “CIS Benchmark for Microsoft
            Windows Server 2012 R2”</t>
          <t>publication date</t>
          <t>overview</t>
          <t>Product category (0..n), such as <list style="symbols">
              <t>Antivirus Software</t>
              <t>Application Server</t>
              <t>Auditing</t>
              <t>Authentication</t>
              <t>Automation/Productivity Application Suite</t>
              <t>Client and Server Encryption</t>
              <t>Configuration Management Software</t>
              <t>Database Management System</t>
              <t>Desktop Application</t>
              <t>Desktop Client</t>
              <t>DHCP Server</t>
              <t>Directory Service</t>
              <t>DNS Server</t>
              <t>Email Server</t>
              <t>Encryption Software</t>
              <t>Enterprise Application</t>
              <t>File Encryption</t>
              <t>Firewall</t>
              <t>Firmware</t>
              <t>Handheld Device</t>
              <t>Identity Management</t>
              <t>Intrusion Detection System</t>
              <t>KVM</t>
              <t>Mail Server</t>
              <t>Malware</t>
              <t>Mobile Solution</t>
              <t>Monitoring</t>
              <t>Multi-Functional Peripheral</t>
              <t>Network Router</t>
              <t>Network Switch</t>
              <t>Office Suite</t>
              <t>Operating System</t>
              <t>Peripheral Device</t>
              <t>Security Server</t>
              <t>Server</t>
              <t>Virtual Machine</t>
              <t>Virtualization Software</t>
              <t>Web Browser</t>
              <t>Web Server</t>
              <t>Wireless Email</t>
              <t>Wireless Network</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Data format requirements">

      <t>This section defines usage guidance and additional requirements related to data formats
        above and beyond those specified in <xref target="RFC8322"/>. The following formats are
        expected to be commonly used to express configuration checklist information. For this
        reason, this document specifies additional requirements to ensure interoperability.</t>

      <section title="Unstructured Formats">
        <t> Several commonly used format are unstructered formats designed for human use, and
          therefore poorly support automation. These formats share the require to express their
          media-type correctly, but beyond that, this document makes only recommendations for their
          use.</t>

        <t>When the following formats are used in the content element of an entry, the rolie:format
          element of that entry MUST match the provided media-type. <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Portable Document Format (PDF)"> application/pdf </t>
            <t hangText="Microsoft Office Word Document"> application/msword </t>
            <t hangText="Microsoft Office Word Document (OpenXML or .docx)">
              application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document </t>
            <!-- TODO complete this list -->
          </list></t>

        <t>When the above formats are used, or when any unstructered data format is used, these
          recommendations SHOULD be followed: <list style="symbol">
            <t>The author of the document is provided in a rolie:property with name
              "content-author".</t>
            <t>The title of the checklist, or in the case where none exists, the name of the file,
              is provided in a rolie:property element with name "checklist-name".</t>
            <!-- TODO fill in recommendations -->
          </list></t>


      </section>

      <section title="Compressed formats">

        <t> Checklists are often distributed in compressed or packaged formats. Here is how we deal
          with that:
          <!-- TODO: figure this out. We will likely define some behavior that links to the automatable formats below.--></t>


      </section>
      <section title="Automatable/Structured Formats">
        <t>OVAL,CVRF,SCAP,XCCDF, (SCAP 2.0 Manifest handling)</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="atom-link-registrations" title="atom:link Extensions">

      <texttable>
        <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

        <c>ancestor</c>
        <c>Links to a configuration checklist supersceded by that described in this entry</c>

        <c>target-platform</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource defining the software subject to this
          configuration checklist entry</c>

      </texttable>

    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="configuration-checklist information-type" anchor="iana-software-descriptor">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE Security Resource Information Type Sub-Registry"
          registry located at <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/category/information-type"/> . </t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: configuration-checklist</t>
            <t>index: TBD</t>
            <t>reference: This document, <xref target="checklist-information-type"/></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="checklist:constributor property">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE URN Parameters" registry located in <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/"/>.</t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: property:checklist:contributor</t>
            <t>Extension IRI: urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:checklist:contributor</t>
            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="rolie-properties"/></t>
            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <!-- TODO: Add the rest of the properties here in the above format-->


      <!--
      <t>New IANA table for “ROLIE Entry Format”</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>scap-1.2</t>
          <t>PDF</t>
          <t>xccdf-1.2-collection</t>
          <t>oval</t>
          <t>cvrf</t>
          <t>cve (should we reuse the enumref?); Look at the “enumref” and see if we can copy/paste
            configuration checklist-specific information in a similar manner? Can we then include
            that enum reference in the ROLIE extension document or should we create a new “enumref”
            document separately?</t>
          <t>vulnerability</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="name:"> configuration-checklist</t>
          <t hangText="index:"> TBD</t>
          <t hangText="reference:"> TBD</t>
        </list></t>
-->


    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Use of this extension requires understanding and managing the security considerations of
        the core ROLIE specification. Beyond that, there must be considerations made for the common
        use cases and data types that would be shared with this extension in particular.</t>

      <t> Checklist information, while typically shared publicly, can have potential security impact
        if compromised. In these cases, the utmost care should be taken to secure the REST endpoint.
        Ensure that only authenticated users are allowed request access to any part of the ROLIE
        repository. Authentication schemes such as OAUTH or basic HTTP Auth provide a signifigant
        barrier to compromise. When providing checklist information as a paid service, security is
        valuable as a means to protect valuable data from being stolen or taken for free. In these
        cases, the above strategies still apply, but providers may want to make the Feed visible to
        non-authenticated users, with meaningful error messages sent to users that have not yet paid
        for the service.</t>

      <t> Typical RESTful security measures applied commonly on the web would be effective to secure
        this ROLIE extension. As a flexible and reletaviely simple RESTful service, ROLIE server
        implementations have great flexibility and freedom in securing their repository.</t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="privacy-considerations" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This extension poses no additonal privacy considerations above and beyond those stated in the core ROLIE specification.</t>

    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC8322; &RFC8174; <reference
        anchor="I-D.ietf-mile-rolie">
        <front>
          <title>Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange</title>

          <author initials="J" surname="Field" fullname="John Field">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="S" surname="Banghart" fullname="Stephen Banghart">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="D" surname="Waltermire" fullname="David Waltermire">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="May" day="26" year="2017"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines a resource-oriented approach for security automation
              information publication, discovery, and sharing. Using this approach, producers may
              publish, share, and exchange representations of software descriptors, security
              incidents, attack indicators, software vulnerabilities, configuration checklists, and
              other security automation information as web-addressable resources. Furthermore,
              consumers and other stakeholders may access and search this security information as
              needed, establishing a rapid and on- demand information exchange network for
              restricted internal use or public access repositories. This specification extends the
              Atom Publishing Protocol and Atom Syndication Format to transport and share security
              automation resource representations.</t>
          </abstract>

        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-mile-rolie-07"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-mile-rolie-07.txt"
        />
      </reference>




    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="NIST_800-53"
        target="http://deusty.blogspot.com/2007/09/stunt-out-of-band-channels.html">
        <front>
          <title>NIST 800-53</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Hanson" fullname="Robbie Hanson">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" month="September" day="17"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="CIS_Critical_Controls"
        target="https://www.cisecurity.org/critical-controls/">
        <front>
          <title>CIS Critical Security Controls</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2016" month="August" day="31"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="PCI_DSS"
        target="https://www.pcisecuritystandards.org/document_library?category=pcidss&amp;document=pci_dss">
        <front>
          <title>PCI Data Security Standard</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2016" month="April"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


    </references>

<section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
  <t> This section provides some brief examples of a Checklist Information Type ROLIE Entry.
    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
      <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
    xmlns:rolie="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rolie-1.0" xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>c8db0a93-4dcb-426e-997f-ba43c100b863</id>
    <title>NIST National Checklist for Red Hat Virtualization Host 4.x</title>
    <published>2020-06-29T18:13:51.0Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-29T18:13:51.0Z</updated>
    <category scheme="urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type" term="checklist"/>
    <summary>SCAP content for evaluation of Red Hat Virtualization Host 4.x systems. The Red Hat content embeds multiple pre-established compliance profiles.</summary>
    <rolie:format ns="scap13namespace"/>
    <content type="application/xml" src="https://nvd.nist.gov/ncp/checklist/908/download/5615"/>
    <link rel="supporting" title="OpenControl-formatted NIST 800-53 responses for Red Hat Virtualization Host 4.x" href="https://github.com/ComplianceAsCode/redhat/tree/master/virtualization-host" type="Machine-Readable Format"/>
    <link rel="supporting" title="[DRAFT] DISA STIG for Red Hat Virtualization Host (RHVH)" href="https://galaxy.ansible.com/RedHatOfficial/rhv4_rhvh_stig" type="Ansible Playbook"/>
    <link rel="supporting" title="VPP - Protection Profile for Virtualization v. 1.0 for Red Hat Virtualization Hypervisor (RHVH)" href="https://galaxy.ansible.com/RedHatOfficial/rhv4_rhvh_vpp" type="Ansible Playbook"/>
    <rolie:property name="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" value="908"/>
    <rolie:property name="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:checklist:checklist-version" value="content v0.1.48"/>
    <rolie:property name="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-published-date" value="01/14/2020"/>
    <rolie:property name="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-updated-date" value=" 	06/14/2019"/>
    <rolie:property name="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:checklist:product-category" value="Virtual Machine"/>
</entry>]]></artwork>
    </figure></t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
