<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY xml-names SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-names-20091208.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5070 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5070.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8322 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-sacm-coswid SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sacm-coswid.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="rfc7749.css"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-sacm-rolie-softwaredescriptor-07">
  <?rfc compact="yes"?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
  <?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ROLIE SWD EXT">Definition of the ROLIE Software Descriptor Extension</title>
    <author fullname="Stephen Banghart" initials="S.B." surname="Banghart">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
          <city>Gaithersburg</city>
          <region>Maryland</region>
          <code>20877</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>stephen.banghart@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="David Waltermire" initials="D.W." surname="Waltermire">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
          <city>Gaithersburg</city>
          <region>Maryland</region>
          <code>20877</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>david.waltermire@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2019"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>SACM Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>rolie</keyword>
    <keyword>software</keyword>
    <keyword>software descriptor</keyword>
    <keyword>swid</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document uses the "information-type" extension point as defined in the
        Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE) <xref target="RFC8322"/> Section
        7.1.2 to better support Software Record and Software Inventory use cases. This specification
        registers a new ROLIE information-type, "software-descriptor", that allows for the
        categorization of information relevant to software description activities and formats. In
        particular, the usage of the ISO 19770-2:2015 Software Identification Tag (SWID Tag) and the
        Concise SWID (COSWID) formats in ROLIE are standardized. Additionally, this document
        discusses requirements and usage of other ROLIE elements in order to best syndicate software
        description information.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="starting-intro">
      <t>This document defines an extension to the Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information
        Exchange (ROLIE) <xref target="RFC8322"/> to support the publication of software descriptor
        information. Software descriptor information is information that characterizes static
        software components, packages, and installers; including identification, version, software
        creation and publication, and file artifact information. </t>

      <t> Software descriptor information provides data about what might be installed, but doesn't
        describe a specific software installation's configuration or execution. This static approach
        to software description is a tightly limited scope that still covers the majority of current
        use cases for software inventory and record keeping.</t>

      <t>Some possible use cases for software descriptor information ROLIE Feeds (Section 6.1 of
          <xref target="RFC8322"/>) include:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Software providers can publish software descriptor information so that software
            researchers, enterprises, and users of software can understand the collection of
            software produced by that software provider.</t>
          <t>Organizations can aggregate and syndicate collections of software descriptor
            information provided by multiple software providers to support software-related analysis
            processes (e.g., vulnerability analysis) and to provide downsteam services (e.g.,
            software configuration checklist repositories).</t>
          <t>End user organizations can consume software descriptor information along with related
            software vulnerability and configuration information to provide the data needed to
            automate software asset, patch, and configuration management practices.</t>
          <t>Organizations can use software descriptors to support verification of other entities
            through integrity measurement mechanisms. </t>
        </list></t>
      <t>This document supports these use cases by describing the content requirements for Feeds and
        Entries of software descriptor information that are to be published to or retrieved from a
        ROLIE repository.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" anchor="ext-terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST," "MUST NOT," "REQUIRED," "SHALL," "SHALL NOT," "SHOULD," "SHOULD NOT,"
        "RECOMMENDED," "MAY," and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
      <t>As an extension of <xref target="RFC8322"/>, this document refers to many terms
        defined in that document. In particular, the use of "Entry" and "Feed" are aligned
        with the definitions presented in section TODO of ROLIE.</t>
      <t>Several places in this document refer to the "information-type" of a Resource (Entry or
        Feed). This refers to the "term" attribute of an "atom:category" element whose scheme is
        "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type". For an Entry, this value can be inherited
        from it's containing Feed as per <xref target="RFC8322"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Background" anchor="background">
      <t> In order to effectively protect and secure an endpoint, it is vital to know what the
        software load of that endpoint is. Software load, the combination of software, patches and
        installers on a device, represents a significant portion of the endpoint's attack surface.
        Unfortunately, without a reliable and secure package manager, or a secured and managed
        operating system with strict software whitelisting, tracking what software is installed on
        an endpoint is currently not feasible without undue effort. Even attempting to whitelist
        software is difficult without a way of identifying software and its editions, versions and
        hotfixes.</t>
      <t>Software descriptor information, such as that standardized in the ISO 19770-2:2015 Software
        Identification Tag (SWID) format or expressed in proprietary enterprise databases, attempts
        to provide as much data about this software as possible. </t>
      <t>Once this information is expressed, it needs to be stored and shared to internal and
        external parties. ROLIE provides a mechanism to handle this sharing in an
        automation-friendly way.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="The &quot;software-descriptor&quot; information type"
      anchor="infotype-software-descriptor">
      <t>When an "atom:category" element has a "scheme" attribute equal to
        "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type", the "term" attribute defines the
        information type of the associated resource. A new valid value for this "term":
        "software-descriptor", is described in this section and registered in <xref
          target="iana-software-descriptor"/>. When this value is used, the resource in question is
        considered to have an information-type of "software-descriptor" as per <xref
          target="RFC8322"/> Section 7.1.2.</t>
      <t>The "software-descriptor" information type represents any static information that describes
        a piece of software. This document uses the definition of software provided by <xref
          target="RFC4949"/>. Note that as per this definition, this information type pertains to
        static software, that is, code on the disc. The "software-descriptor" information type is
        intended to provide a category for information that does one or more of the following:<list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="identifies and characterizes software:"> information that provides quantative
            and qualitative data describing software. This information identifies and charaterizes a
            given instance of software.</t>
          <t hangText="provides software installer metadata:"> information about software used to
            install other software. This metadata identifies, and characterizes a software
            installation package or media.</t>
          <t hangText="describes stateless installation metadata:"> information that describes the
            software post-deployment, such as files that may be deployed during an installation. It
            is expected that this metadata is produced generally for a given installation, and may
            not exactly match the actual installed files on a given endpoint.</t>
        </list></t>
      <t> Provided below is a non-exhaustive list of information that may be considered to be of a
        software-descriptor information type. <list style="symbols">
          <t>Naming information: IDs and names that aid in the identification of a piece of software </t>
          <t>Version and patching information: Version numbers, patch identifiers, or other
            information that relates to software updates and patches. </t>
          <t>Vendor and source information: Includes where the software was developed or
            distributed, as well as where the software installation media may be located.</t>
          <t>Payload and file information: information that describes or enumerates the files and
            folders that make up the piece of software, and information about those files.</t>
          <t>Descriptive information and data: Any information that otherwise characterizes a piece
            of software, such as libraries, runtime environments, target operating systems, intended
            purpose or audience, etc.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>It is important to note that software descriptor information is static for a given piece of
        software. That is, the information expressed is the data that doesn't change from the
        publication of the software to its final install. Information about the current status (e.g.
        install location, memory usage, CPU usage, launch parameters, job progress, etc.), is out of
        scope of this information type.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="rolie:property Extensions">
      <t>This document registers new valid rolie:property names as follows:</t>
      <section title="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swname" anchor="prop-swd-swname">
        <t>This property provides an exposure point for the plain text name of the software being
          described. Naming of software is not a well standardized process, and software names can
          change between product versions or editions. As such, care should be taken that this value
          is set as consistently as possible by generating it directly from an attached software
          descriptor resource.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swversion" anchor="prop-swd-swversion">
        <t>This property provides an exposure point for the version of the software being described.
          This value should be generated or taken from the software descriptor linked to by the
          entry. This helps avoid, but does not prevent, inconsistent versioning schemes being
          shared.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swcreator" anchor="prop-swd-swcreator">
        <t>This property provides an exposure point for a plain text name of the creator of the
          software being described. This is in many cases an organization or company, but certainly
          could be a single person. Most software descriptor formats include this information, and
          where possible, this property should be set equal to that value.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Data format requirements" anchor="ext-synd-format">
      <t>This section defines usage guidance and additional requirements related to data formats
        above and beyond those specified in <xref target="RFC8322"/>. The following formats are
        expected to be commonly used to express software descriptor information. For this reason,
        this document specifies additional requirements to ensure interoperability.</t>
      <section title="The ISO SWID 2015 format" anchor="ext-synd-format-iso2016">
        <section title="Description">
          <t>ISO/IEC 19770-2:2015 defines a software record data format referred to as a "SWID Tag".
            It provides several tag types: <list style="symbols">
              <t>primary: provides descriptive and naming information about software, </t>
              <t>patch: describes non-standalone software meant to patch existing software, </t>
              <t>corpus: describes the software installation media that installs a given piece of
                software,</t>
              <t>supplemental: provides additional metadata to be deployed alongside a tag. </t>
            </list></t>
          <t>For a more complete overview as well as normative requirements, refer to ISO/IEC
            19770-2:2015 <xref target="SWID"/>.</t>
          <t> For additional requirements and guidance around creation of SWID Tags, consult NIST
            Internal Report 8060 <xref target="NISTIR8060"/>. </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Requirements">
          <t> For an Entry to be considered as a "SWID Tag Entry", it MUST fulfill the following
            conditions: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The information-type of the Entry is "software-descriptor". For a typical Entry,
                this is derived from the information type of the Feed it is contained in. For a
                standalone Entry, this is provided by an "atom:category" element.</t>
              <t>The document linked to by the "href" attribute of the "atom:content" element is a
                2015 SWID Tag per ISO/IEC 19770-2:2015. </t>
            </list></t>
          <t>A "SWID Tag Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element MUST be
                "application/xml".</t>
              <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value" attribute exactly equal
                to the "&lt;tagid&gt;" element in the attached SWID Tag. This allows ROLIE consumers
                to more easily search for SWID tags without needing to download the tag itself.</t>
              <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swname", and the "value" attribute equal to the
                value of the "&lt;name&gt;" element in the attached SWID Tag. As above, this helps
                ROLIE consumers search and filter Entries.</t>

              <t>There MAY be a property element with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swversion". When this property appears, its
                value MUST be equal to the value of the "version" element in the attached SWID
                Tag.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="the-concise-swid-format" title="The Concise SWID format">
        <section title="Description">
          <t>The Concise SWID (COSWID) format is an alternative representation of the SWID Tag
            format using a Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) encoding. CBOR provides the
            format with a reduced size that is more suitable for constrained devices. COSWID provides
            the same features and attributes as are specified in ISO 19770-2:2015, plus: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>a straight forward method to sign and encrypt using COSE, and</t>
              <t>additional attributes that provide an improved structure to include file hashes
                intended to be used as Reference Integrity Measurements (RIM).</t>
            </list></t>
          <t>For more information and the complete specification, refer to the COSWID internet draft
              <xref target="I-D.ietf-sacm-coswid"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Requirements">
          <t> For an Entry to be considered as a "COSWID Tag Entry", it MUST fulfill the following
            conditions: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The information-type of the Entry is "software-descriptor". For a typical Entry,
                this is derived from the information-type of the Feed it is contained in. For a
                standalone Entry, this is provided by an "atom:category" element.</t>
              <t>The document linked to by the "href" attribute of the "atom:content" element is a
                COSWID Tag per <xref target="I-D.ietf-sacm-coswid"/>
              </t>
            </list></t>
          <t>A "COSWID Tag Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list style="symbols">
              <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the atom:content element MUST be
                "application/coswid+cbor".</t>
              <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value" attribute exactly equal
                to the "tag-id" element in the attached COSWID Tag (mapped to integer 0). This
                allows ROLIE consumers to more easily search for COSWID tags without needing to
                download the tag itself.</t>
              <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swname", and the "value" attribute equal to the
                value of the "swid-name" element in the attached COSWID Tag (mapped to the integer
                1). As above, this helps ROLIE consumers search and filter
                Entries.</t>
              <t>There MAY be a property element with the "name" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swversion". When this property appears, it's
                value MUST be equal to the value of the tag-version element in the attached COSWID
                Tag (mapped to the integer 12).</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="atom:link Extensions" anchor="ext-synd-entries-link">
      <t>This section defines additional link relationships that implementations MUST support. These
        relationships are not registered in the Link Relation IANA table as their use case is too
        narrow. Each relationship is named and described.</t>
      <texttable anchor="links-software-descriptor-table"
        title="Link Relations for Resource-Oriented Lightweight Indicator Exchange" style="all">
        <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
        <c>ancestor</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines an ancestor of the software being
          described by this Entry. This is usually a previous version of the software.</c>
        <c>descendent</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines an descendent of the software being
          described by this Entry. This is usually a more recent version or edition of the
          software.</c>
        <c>patches</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines the software being patched by this
          software</c>
        <c>patchedby</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines the patch or update itself that can
          be or has been applied to this software.</c>
        <c>requires</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines a piece of software required for
          this software to function properly, i.e., a dependency. </c>
        <c>requiredBy</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines a piece of software that requires
          this software to function properly. </c>
        <c>installs</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines the software that is installed by
          this software.</c>
        <c>installedBy</c>
        <c>Links to a software descriptor resource that defines the software package that installs
          this software.</c>
        <c>patchesVulnerability</c>
        <c>Links to a vulnerability that this software update fixes. Used for software descriptors
          that describe software patches or updates.</c>
        <c>hasVulnerability</c>
        <c>Links to a vulnerability description object that details a vulnerability that this
          software has.</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="software-descriptor information-type" anchor="iana-software-descriptor">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE Security Resource Information Type Sub-Registry"
          registry located at <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/category/information-type"/> . </t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: software-descriptor</t>
            <t>index: TBD</t>
            <t>reference: This document, <xref target="infotype-software-descriptor"/></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="swd:swname property">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE URN Parameters" registry located in <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/"/>.</t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: property:swd:swname</t>
            <t>Extension IRI: urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swname</t>
            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="prop-swd-swname"/></t>
            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="swd:swversion property">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE URN Parameters" registry located in <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/"/>.</t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: property:swd:swversion</t>
            <t>Extension IRI: urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swversion</t>
            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="prop-swd-swname"/></t>
            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="swd:swcreator property">
        <t>IANA has added an entry to the "ROLIE URN Parameters" registry located in <eref
            target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/"/>.</t>
        <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
            <t>name: property:swd:swcreator</t>
            <t>Extension IRI: urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swcreator</t>
            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="prop-swd-swname"/></t>
            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Use of this extension implies dealing with the security implications of both ROLIE and of
        software descriptors in general. As with any data, care should be taken to verify the
        trustworthiness and veracity of the descriptor information to the fullest extent possible. </t>
      <t>Ideally, software descriptors should be signed by the software manufacturer, or
        signed by whichever agent processed the source code. Software descriptor documents from
        these sources are more likely to be accurate than those generated by scraping installed
        software. </t>
      <t>These "authoritative" sources of software descriptor content should consider additional
        security for their ROLIE repository beyond the typical recommendations, as the central
        importance of the repository is likely to make it a target.</t>
      <t>Version information is often represented differently across manufacturers and even across
        product releases. If using software version information for low fault tolerance comparisons
        and searches, care should be taken that the correct version scheme is being used.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"
      >&RFC2119;&RFC5070;&RFC4949;&RFC8322;&I-D.ietf-sacm-coswid; &RFC8174;<reference target="https://www.iso.org/standard/65666.html" anchor="SWID">
        <front>
          <title >Information technology - Software asset management - Part 2: Software
            identification tag</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2015" month="October" day="01"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="19770-2:2015"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="NISTIR8060" target="https://doi.org/10.6028/NIST.IR.8060">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for the Creation of Interoperable Software Identification (SWID)
            Tags</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Waltermire" fullname="David Waltermire">
            <organization>National Institute for Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B.A." surname="Cheikes" fullname="Brant A. Cheikes">
            <organization>The MITRE Corporation</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Feldman" fullname="Larry Feldman">
            <organization>G2, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Witte" fullname="Greg Witte">
            <organization>G2, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2016" month="April"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="NISTIR" value="8060"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section title="Schema" anchor="appendix-schema">
      <t>This document does not require any schema extensions.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Examples of Use">
      <t>Use of this extension in a ROLIE repository will not typically change that repository's
        operation. As such, the general examples provided by the ROLIE core document would serve as
        examples. Provided below is a sample software descriptor ROLIE entry: </t>
      <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
  <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:rolie="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rolie-1.0">
    <id>dd786dba-88e6-440b-9158-b8fae67ef67c</id>
    <title>Sample Software Descriptor</title>
    <published>2015-08-04T18:13:51.0Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-05T18:13:51.0Z</updated>
    <summary>A descriptor for a piece of software published by this
    organization. </summary>
    <link rel="self" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/SWD/123456"/>
    <link rel="feed" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/SWD/"/>
    <link rel="requires" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/SWD/78430"/>
    <rolie:property name=urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:swd:swname
        value="Example Software Name"/>
    <category
        scheme="urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type"
        term="software-descriptor"/>
    <rolie:format 
        ns="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19770/-2/2015/schema.xsd"/>
    <content type="application/xml" 
        src="http://www.example.org/rolie/SWD/123456/data"/>
  </entry>]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
