<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY xml-names SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-names-20091208.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2141 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2141.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2616 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3444 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3444.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3688 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4287 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml">

  <!ENTITY RFC5023 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5023.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5005 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5005.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6545 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6545.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6546 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6546.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8322 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8322.xml">

]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mile-rolie-vuln-03">
    <!-- Working draft of supporting document for ROLIE -->
    <?rfc compact="yes"?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
    <?rfc toc="yes"?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="ROLIE Vuln">Definition of the ROLIE Vulnerability Extension</title>
        <author initials="S.A." surname="Banghart" fullname="Stephen A. Banghart">
            <organization abbrev="NIST">National Institute of Standards and
                Technology</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
                    <city>Gaithersburg</city>
                    <region>Maryland</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>(301)975-4288</phone>
                <email>stephen.banghart@nist.gov</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2019"/>
        <area>Security</area>
        <workgroup>MILE Working Group</workgroup>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document extends the Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE)
                core to add the information type categories and related requirements needed to
                support Vulnerability use cases. Additional categories, properties, and requirements
                based on content type enables a higher level of interoperability between ROLIE
                implementations, and richer metadata for ROLIE consumers. In particular, usage of
                the Common Vulnerability Enumeration (CVE) <xref target="cve"/> format is discussed.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="starting-intro">

            <t>As our software becomes more complex and interconnected, the number of software
                vulnerabilities exploitable by actors with mal-intent has skyrocketed. Huge amounts
                of resources have been poured into the preemptive discovery, description, and
                remediation of these vulnerabilities, but it is often a challenge to share and
                communicate the results of these efforts. While bad-actors have vast collaboration
                networks that enable widespread knowledge of any vulnerability, the defensive
                community at large has no sharing consortium as prevalent. If we are to keep up with
                the rising difficulty of defending our systems, we must increase our ability to
                quickly, efficiently, and automatically share information about vulnerabilities. </t>

            <t>The Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE) <xref target="RFC8322"
                /> provides a means to share computer security information with an eye towards
                automation and efficiency. By utilizing ROLIE to share vulnerability data, we get
                one step closer to establishing automated communication between each party involved
                in fighting vulnerabilities. A security researcher can send a newly discovered
                vulnerability to a vulnerability repository, where it is automatically retrieved and
                consumed by enterprise systems. At this final stage, the enterprise can
                cross-reference against their enterprise wide software load to begin mitigating the
                issue.</t>

            <t> This extension to ROLIE introduces new requirements and IANA registrations to allow
                ROLIE repositories to share vulnerability data in a standardized and compatible
                way.</t>

            <t>This extension does not attempt to solve the vulnerability data format issue, as this
                work is being done across standards groups and industry consortiums. Instead, this
                extension serves to address the problem of sharing these data formats to downstream
                consumers in a automated and efficient fashion.</t>


        </section>
        <section title="Terminology" anchor="ext-terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST," "MUST NOT," "REQUIRED," "SHALL," "SHALL NOT," "SHOULD," "SHOULD
                NOT," "RECOMMENDED," "MAY," and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in <xref target="RFC8174"/>. </t>
            <t>As an extension of <xref target="RFC8322"/>, this document refers to many terms
                defined in that document. In particular, the use of "Entry" and "Feed" are aligned
                with the definitions presented there.</t>
            <t>Several places in this document refer to the "information-type" of a Resource (Entry
                or Feed). This refers to the "term" attribute of an "atom:category" element whose
                scheme is "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type". For an Entry, this
                value can be inherited from it's containing Feed as per <xref target="RFC8322"
                />.</t>
            <t>This document uses the definition of "vulnerability" given by <xref target="RFC4949"/>. </t>
        </section>
        <section title="The &quot;vulnerability&quot; information type"
            anchor="infotype-vulnerability">
            <t>When an "atom:category" element has a "scheme" attribute equal to
                "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type", the "term" attribute defines the
                information type of the associated resource. A new valid value for this attribute:
                "vulnerability", is described in this section, and registered in <xref
                    target="iana-it-vuln"/>. When this value is used, the resource in question is
                considered to have an information-type of "vulnerability" as per <xref
                    target="RFC8322"/> Section 7.1.2.</t>
            <t>The "vulnerability" information-type represents any information describing or
                pertaining to a computer security vulnerability. This document uses the definition
                of vulnerability provided by <xref target="RFC4949"/>. Provided below is a
                non-exhaustive list of information that may be considered to be of a vulnerability
                information type. <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Fundamental identifying information, such as a global ID or number, that
                        identifies a given vulnerability.</t>
                    <t>Descriptive information, including but not limited to: <list>
                            <t>Severity scoring - using some standardized scoring algorithm or
                                otherwise,</t>
                            <t>Execution details - how the vulnerability is exploited</t>
                            <t>Impact - what the consequences are of this vulnerability</t>
                            <t>History and provenance data - when was the vulnerability discovered,
                                when was it reported and to whom,</t>
                            <t>Plain text description of any of the above</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>Metadata attached to a vulnerability, such as information about the entity
                        that discovered or described the vulnerability.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>Note again that this list is not exhaustive: any information that is in the abstract
                realm of a vulnerability should be classified under this information-type. The final
                decision as to the information type of an Entry is up to the provider and author of
                the Entry.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Common Vulnerability Enumeration (CVE) Format" anchor="ext-synd-format">
            <section title="Description">
                <t>The Common Vulnerability Enumeration (CVE) provides a globally unique identifier
                    for vulnerabilities. Each CVE provides a CVE-ID, by which a vulnerability can be
                    referred to in any context, as well as descriptive information about that
                    vulnerability. </t>
                <t>For more information and in-depth specifications, please see <xref target="cve"
                    />.</t>
                <t>CVE provides a valuable set of information fields, but itself does not provide a
                    standardized data format. This extension provides standardization around two
                    common serializations of the CVE standard, both used by the National Institute
                    of Standards and Technology (NIST) National Vulnerability Database (NVD). The
                    NVD provides a repository of "CVE Entries" available in either serialization
                    format. The first format is XML-based: the NIST NVD CVE Entry format <xref
                        target="nvdcvexml"/>, and the second is JSON-based: NIST NVD JSON CVE Entry
                    Format <xref target="nvdcvejson"/>. These two representations of a CVE are
                    equivalent, and can be losslessly converted.</t>
                <t>This section defines usage guidance and additional requirements above and beyond
                    those specified in <xref target="RFC8322"/> that apply when CVE data formats are
                    in use. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Requirements">
                <t> For an Entry to be considered a "CVE Entry", it MUST fulfill the following
                    conditions: <list style="symbols">
                        <t>The information-type of the Entry is "vulnerability". For a typical
                            Entry, this is derived from the information type of the Feed it is
                            contained in. For a standalone Entry, this is provided by an
                            "atom:category" element.</t>
                        <t>The document linked to by the "ref" attribute of the "atom:content"
                            element is a CVE Entry as defined by either <xref target="nvdcvexml"/>
                            or <xref target="nvdcvejson"/>. Other well-defined CVE serializations
                            would be valid but would not be subject to the following requirements,
                            reducing their interoperability. </t>
                    </list></t>
                <t>The XML and JSON NVD formats follow different requirements. </t>
                <t>A "XML CVE Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list
                        style="symbols">
                        <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element MUST be
                            "application/xml".</t>
                        <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                            "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value" attribute
                            exactly equal to the "&lt;name&gt;" element in the attached CVE Entry.
                            This allows for ROLIE consumers to more easily search for CVE Entries
                            without needing to download the entry itself.</t>
                    </list></t>
                <t>A "JSON CVE Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list
                        style="symbols">
                        <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element MUST be
                            "application/json".</t>
                        <t>There MUST be one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute equal to
                            "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value" attribute
                            exactly equal to the "cve:{cve_data_meta":{ID}}" element in the attached
                            CVE Entry. This allows for ROLIE consumers to more easily search for CVE
                            Entries without needing to download the entry itself.</t>
                    </list></t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Link relations for the 'vulnerability'
                information-type"
            anchor="links-inc">
            <t> The atom:link element contains a "rel" attribute that describes the semantic meaning
                of the given link.</t>
            <t>If the category of an Entry is the vulnerability information type, then the following
                link relations MUST be respected, that is, not removed, by the server.
                Implementations can provide extra functionality by understanding the semantic
                meaning of these relations.</t>
            <texttable anchor="links-inc-table"
                title="Link Relations for Resource-Oriented Lightweight Indicator Exchange">
                <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
                <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
                <c>severity</c>
                <c>Links to a document describing or scoring the severity of this vulnerability.</c>

            </texttable>
        </section>


        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
            <section title="information-type registrations" anchor="iana-it">
                <t>IANA has added the following entries to the "ROLIE Security Resource Information
                    Type Sub-Registry" registry located at <eref
                        target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/category/information-type"/>
                    . </t>
                <section title="vulnerability information-type" anchor="iana-it-vuln">

                    <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
                            <t>name: vulnerability</t>
                            <t>index: TBD</t>
                            <t>reference: This document, <xref target="infotype-vulnerability"/></t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>All security considerations of the core ROLIE document apply to use of this
                extension.</t>
            <t>The use of this particular extension implies the use of ROLIE in sharing
                vulnerability information. In automated use cases, downstream consumers may be
                dynamically acquiring and acting on vulnerabilities posted to a ROLIE repository. In
                this case, a compromised server could serve up false vulnerability information to
                trigger dangerous activity in automated consumers. Automatic remediation solutions
                that consume shared vulnerability information in high risk use cases should take
                care to verify data before taking action. If some global ID, such as a CVE-ID, is
                included, this verification should be trivial.</t>
        </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC8322; &RFC4949; &RFC5023; &RFC4287; &RFC8174;
                <reference anchor="cve" target="https://cve.mitre.org/about/index.html">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="CVE">Common Vulnerability Enumeration</title>
                    <author> <organization abbrev="MITRE">The MITRE Corporation</organization> </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="cvexml" target="https://cve.mitre.org/schema/cve/cve_1.0.xsd">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="CVE-XML"/>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="MITRE">The MITRE Corporation</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="nvdcvexml" target="https://csrc.nist.gov/schema/nvd/nvdcve.xsdf">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="NVD-CVE-XML">NVD CVE Entry XML Schema</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="NIST">National Institute of Standards and
                            Technology</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="nvdcvejson"
                target="https://csrc.nist.gov/schema/nvd/feed/1.0/nvd_cve_feed_json_1.0.schema">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="NVD-CVE-JSON">NVD CVE Entry JSON Schema</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="NIST">National Institute of Standards and
                            Technology</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
