<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY xml-names SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-names-20091208.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2141 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2141.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2616 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3444 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3444.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3688 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4287 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5070 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5070.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5023 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5023.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5005 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5005.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6545 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6545.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6546 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6546.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5070bis SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mile-rfc5070-bis-25.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8322 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8322.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC7970 SYSTEM
  "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7970.xml">
    <!ENTITY misp SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-dulaunoy-misp-core-format-07.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mile-rolie-csirt-06">
    <!-- Working draft of supporting document for ROLIE -->
    <?rfc compact="yes"?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
    <?rfc toc="yes"?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="ROLIE CSIRT">Definition of ROLIE CSIRT Extension</title>
        <author initials="S.A." surname="Banghart" fullname="Stephen A. Banghart">
            <organization abbrev="NIST">National Institute of Standards and
                Technology</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
                    <city>Gaithersburg</city>
                    <region>Maryland</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>(301)975-4288</phone>
                <email>sab3@nist.gov</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J.P." surname="Field" fullname="John P. Field">
            <organization abbrev="Pivotal">Pivotal Software, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>625 Avenue of the Americas</street>
                    <city>New York</city>
                    <region>New York</region>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>(646)792-5770</phone>
                <email>jfield@pivotal.io</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2019"/>
        <area>Security</area>
        <workgroup>MILE Working Group</workgroup>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document extends the Resource-Oriented Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE)
                core to add the Indicator and Incident information types, relevant categories, and related requirements needed to
                support Computer Security Incident Response Team (CSIRT) use cases. Additional
                supporting requirements are also defined that describe the use of specific formats
                and link relations pertaining to the new information types.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="starting-intro">
            <t>Threats to computer security are evolving ever more rapidly as time goes on. As
                software increases in complexity, the number of vulnerabilities in systems and
                networks can increase exponentially. Threat actors looking to exploit these
                vulnerabilities are making more frequent and more widely distributed attacks across
                a large variety of systems. The adoption of liberal information sharing amongst
                attackers allows a discovered vulnerability to be shared and used to attack a
                vulnerable system within a narrow window of time. As the skills and knowledge
                required to identify and combat these attacks become more and more specialized, even
                a well established and secure system may find itself unable to quickly respond to an
                incident. Effective identification of and response to a sophisticated attack
                requires open cooperation and collaboration between defending operators, software
                vendors, and end-users. To improve the timeliness of responses, automation must be
                used to acquire, contextualize, and put to use shared computer security
                information.</t>

            <t> Computer Security Incident Response Teams (CSIRTs) share two primary forms of information: incidents and indicators. Using these
                forms of information, analysts are able to perform a wide range of activities both
                proactive and reactive to improve the security of their systems. </t>
            <t>Incident information describes a cyber security incident. Such information may
                include attack characteristics, information about the attacker, and attack vector
                data. Sharing this information helps analysts within the sharing community to
                inoculate their systems against similar attacks, providing proactive protection.</t>

            <t>Indicator information describes the symptoms or necessary pre-conditions of an
                attack. Everything from system vulnerabilities to unexpected network traffic can
                help analysts secure systems and prepare for an attack. Making this information
                available for sharing aids in the proactive defense of systems both within an
                operating unit but also for any CSIRTs that are part of a sharing consortium.</t>

            <t>As a means to bring automation of content discovery and dissemination into the CSIRT
                domain, this specification provides an extension to the Resource-Oriented
                Lightweight Information Exchange (ROLIE) core <xref target="RFC8322"/> designed to
                address CSIRT use cases. The primary purpose of this extension is to define two new
                information types: incident, and indicator, along with formats and link relations
                that support these information-types.</t>

        </section>
        <section title="Terminology" anchor="ext-terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST," "MUST NOT," "REQUIRED," "SHALL," "SHALL NOT," "SHOULD," "SHOULD
                NOT," "RECOMMENDED," "MAY," and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in <xref target="RFC8174"/>. </t>
            <t>Definitions for some of the common computer security-related terminology used in this
                document can be found in Section 2 of <xref target="RFC5070"/>.</t>
            <t>As an extension of <xref target="RFC8322"/>, this document refers to many terms
                defined in that document. In particular, the use of "Entry" and "Feed" are aligned
                with the definitions presented there.</t>
            <t>Several places in this document refer to the "information-type" of a Resource (Entry
                or Feed). This refers to the "term" attribute of an "atom:category" element whose
                scheme is "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type". For an Entry, this
                value can be inherited from it's containing Feed as per <xref target="RFC8322"
                />.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Information-type Extensions" anchor="infotype">
            <section title="The &quot;incident&quot; information type" anchor="infotype-incident">
                <t>When an "atom:category" element has a "scheme" attribute equal to
                    "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type", the "term" attribute defines
                    the information type of the associated resource. A new valid "term" value for
                    this "scheme": "incident", is described in this section, and registered in <xref
                        target="iana-incident"/>.</t>
                <t>The &quot;incident&quot; information type represents any information describing
                    or pertaining to a computer security incident. This document uses the definition
                    of incident provided by <xref target="RFC4949"/>. Provided below is a
                    non-exhaustive list of information that may be considered to be an incident
                    information type. <list style="symbols">
                        <t>Timing information: start and end times for the incident and/or the
                            response.</t>
                        <t>Descriptive information: plain text or machine readable data that
                            provides some degree of description of the incident itself.</t>
                        <t>Response information: the methods and results of a response to the
                            incident.</t>
                        <t>Meta and contact information: data about the CSIRT that recorded the
                            information, or the operator that enacted the response.</t>
                        <t>Effect and result information: data that describes the effects of an
                            incident, or what the final results of the incident are.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>Note again that this list is not exhaustive, any information that is in the
                    abstract realm of an incident should be classified under this
                    information-type.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="The &quot;indicator&quot; information type" anchor="infotype-indicator">
                <t>When an "atom:category" element has a "scheme" attribute equal to
                    "urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type", the "term" attribute defines
                    the information type of the associated resource. A new valid "term" value for
                    this "scheme": "indicator", is described in this section, and registered in
                        <xref target="iana-indicator"/>.</t>
                <t> The &quot;indicator&quot; information type represents computer security
                    indicators or any information surrounding them. This document uses the
                    definition of indicator provided by <xref target="RFC4949"/>. Some examples of
                    indicator information are provided below, but note that indicator is defined in
                    an abstract sense, to be understood as a flexible and widely-applicable
                    definition. <list style="symbols">
                        <t>Specific vulnerabilities that indicate a vector for attack.</t>
                        <t>Signs of malicious reconnaissance.</t>
                        <t>Definitions of patterns of other indicators.</t>
                        <t>Events that may indicate an attack and information regarding those
                            events.</t>
                        <t>Meta information about the collecting agent.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>This list is intended to provide examples of the indicator information-type, not
                    to define it.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Data format requirements" anchor="ext-synd-format">
            <t>This section defines usage guidance and additional requirements related to data
                formats above and beyond those specified in <xref target="RFC8322"/>. The following
                formats are expected to be commonly used to express software descriptor information.
                For this reason, this document specifies additional requirements to ensure
                interoperability.</t>
            <section title="Incident Object Description Exchange Format"
                anchor="ext-synd-format-iodef">
                <section title="Description">
                    <t>The Incident Object Description Exchange Format (IODEF) is a format for
                        representing computer security information commonly exchanged between
                        Computer Security Incident Response Teams (CSIRTs) or other operational
                        security teams. </t>
                    <t>IODEF conveys indicators, incident reports, response activities, and related
                        meta-data in an XML serialization. This information is formally structured
                        in order to support and encourage automated machine-to-machine security
                        communication, as well as enhanced processing at the endpoint.</t>
                    <t>The full IODEF specification <xref target="RFC7970"/> provides further
                        high-level discussion and technical details.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Requirements">
                    <t> For an Entry to be considered as a "IODEF Entry", it MUST fulfill the
                        following conditions: <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The information-type of the Entry is "indicator" or "incident". For a
                                typical Entry, this is derived from the information type of the Feed
                                it is contained in. For a standalone Entry, this is provided by an
                                "atom:category" element.</t>

                            <t>The document linked to by the "href" attribute of the "atom:content"
                                element is an IODEF document as per <xref target="RFC7970"/>
                            </t>
                        </list></t>
                    <t>A "IODEF Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list
                            style="symbols">
                            <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element MUST
                                be "application/xml".</t>
                            <t>There MUST be at least one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute
                                equal to "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value"
                                attribute exactly equal to the "&lt;Indicator-ID&gt;" or the
                                "&lt;Incident-ID&gt;" element in the attached IODEF document. This
                                allows for ROLIE consumers to more easily search for IODEF documents
                                without needing to download the document itself.</t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Structured Threat Information eXpression (STIX) Format"
                anchor="ext-synd-format-stix">
                <section title="Description">
                    <t> STIX is a structured language for describing a wide range of security
                        resources. STIX approaches the problem with a focus on flexibility,
                        automation, readability, and extensibility. </t>
                    <t>The full STIX specification <xref target="stix2"/> provides further
                        high-level discussion and technical details.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Requirements">
                    <t> For an Entry to be considered as a "STIX Entry", it MUST fulfill the
                        following conditions: <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The information-type of the Entry is "indicator" or "incident". For a
                                typical Entry, this is derived from the information type of the Feed
                                it is contained in. For a standalone Entry, this is provided by an
                                "atom:category" element.</t>

                            <t>The document linked to by the "href" attribute of the "atom:content"
                                element is a STIX object as per <xref target="stix2"/>
                            </t>
                        </list></t>
                    <t>A "STIX Entry" MUST conform to the following requirements: <list
                            style="symbols">
                            <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element MUST
                                be "application/xml" or "application/json".</t>
                            <t>There MUST be at least one "rolie:property" with the "name" attribute
                                equal to "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and the "value"
                                attribute exactly equal to the "&lt;id&gt;" element in the attached
                                STIX object . This allows for ROLIE consumers to more easily search
                                for STIX objects without needing to download the document
                                itself.</t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Malware Information Sharing Platform (MISP) Format">
                <t>MISP involves documentation, utilities, and formats designed to facilitate the
                    day-to-day duties of security operators. MISP includes it's own data format that
                    is used to share between MISP features. While MISP has Feed features that can
                    share and distribute events, it has support for linking to other sharing methods
                    like ROLIE.</t>
                <t> MISP is defined by a family of internet drafts currently being developed in the IETF.
                    With that in mind, this extension will provide non-normative guidance on using
                    MISP format data in ROLIE. In the future, when the MISP format is formally
                    published, this document will be updated to normative requirements around MISP
                    content. </t>
                <section title="Creating MISP Event Entries">
                    <t>MISP content should be syndicated in ROLIE using the following guidance:<list
                            style="symbols">
                            <t>The information-type of the Entry is "indicator". For a typical
                                Entry, this is derived from the information type of the Feed it is
                                contained in. For a standalone Entry, this is provided by an
                                "atom:category" element.</t>
                            <t>The document linked to by the "href" attribute of the "atom:content"
                                element is a MISP Event object as per <xref
                                    target="I-D.dulaunoy-misp-core-format"/>
                            </t>
                            <t>The value of the "type" attribute of the "atom:content" element
                                should be "application/xml".</t>
                            <t>There should be at least one "rolie:property" with the "name"
                                attribute equal to "urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id" and
                                the "value" attribute exactly equal to the "&lt;uuid&gt;" element in
                                the attached MISP Event. This allows for ROLIE consumers to more
                                easily search for MISP Events without needing to download the
                                document itself.</t>
                            <t> It is also recommended to expose information in the ROLIE Entry that
                                is required and recommended to expose in the MISP Manifest format.
                                This ensures better compatibility between a ROLIE Feed and a MISP
                                Manifest. <list>
                                    <t> The following fields are required by the MISP draft: info,
                                        Orgc, timestamp, date </t>
                                    <t> The following fields are recommended by the MISP draft:
                                        analysis, threat_level_id </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>

                        </list></t>
                </section>
                <section title="MISP Feeds and Manifests">
                    <t>MISP Feeds are hosted lists of MISP events, each event represented by its
                        UUID. Users request Events on a one-by-one basis and are served the full
                        Event on each request.</t>
                    <t>MISP Manifest files list MISP events by their UUIDs as well, but provide a
                        variety of metadata for each Event inline. After examining the minimized and
                        stripped Event in the manifest, a user could search for the Event UUID of
                        interest in a locally located folder of Event files where the file name is
                        the UUID of the Event.</t>
                    <t>ROLIE hosting MISP data would operate as a combination of these approaches.
                        Each ROLIE Feed would contain a list of Event Entries, each with metadata
                        and identifying information about a given Event. Should the user be
                        interested in the Event, the Event Entry provides a direct link to download
                        the full Event. In short, a ROLIE MISP Feed is minimally mappable to a MISP
                        Manifest file where a resolvable link to the MISP Event was injected into
                        each Event described in the Manifest.</t>
                    <t>With that in mind, a MISP Feed as well as a MISP Manifest with attached local
                        file list could be fully converted and hosted as a ROLIE repository. As a
                        lower overhead alternative, a ROLIE server could simply provide a view into
                        MISP data.</t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="atom:link Extensions" anchor="ext-synd-entries-link">
            <t>This section defines additional link relationships that implementations MUST support.
                These relationships are not registered in the Link Relation IANA table as their use
                case is too narrow. Each relationship is named and described.</t>
            <t>These relations come in related pairs. The first of each pair is expected to be more
                common, as they can be determined at the time that the Entry is created. The second
                of each pair will often need to be added retroactively to an Entry.</t>
            <section title="Link relations for the 'incident'
                information-type"
                anchor="links-inc">
                <t>If a ROLIE server supports the incident information-type, then these link
                    relations MUST be supported.</t>

                <texttable anchor="links-inc-table"
                    title="Link Relations for Resource-Oriented Lightweight Indicator Exchange">
                    <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

                    <c>indicators</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more instances of cyber security
                        indicators that are associated with the resource.</c>

                    <c>evidence</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that provides some
                        proof of attribution for an incident. The evidence may or may not have any
                        identified chain of custody.</c>

                    <c>attacker</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that provides a
                        representation of the attacker.</c>

                    <c>vector</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that provides a
                        representation of the method used by the attacker.</c>

                </texttable>
            </section>
            <section title="Link relations for the 'indicator'
                information-type"
                anchor="links-ind">
                <t>If a ROLIE server supports the indicator information-type, then these link
                    relations MUST be supported.</t>

                <texttable anchor="links-ind-table"
                    title="Link Relations for Resource-Oriented Lightweight Indicator Exchange">
                    <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
                    <c>incidents</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more instances of incident
                        representations associated with the resource.</c>

                </texttable>
            </section>
            <section title="Link relations for both information-types" anchor="links-both">
                <t>If a ROLIE server supports either the incident or the indicator
                    information-types, then these link relations MUST be supported.</t>
                <texttable anchor="links-both-table"
                    title="Link Relations for Resource-Oriented Lightweight Indicator Exchange">
                    <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

                    <c>assessments</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that represent the
                        results of executing a benchmark.</c>

                    <c>reports</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that represent RID
                        reports.</c>

                    <c>traceRequests</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that represent RID
                        traceRequests.</c>

                    <c>investigationRequests</c>
                    <c>Provides a link to a collection of zero or more resources that represent RID
                        investigationRequests.</c>
                </texttable>
            </section>

        </section>
        <section title="atom:category Extensions">
            <section title="Newly registered category values" anchor="iodefcategory">
                <t> This document registers two additional registered atom:category names:
                    'urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:purpose' and
                    'urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:restriction'. These categories
                    expose important information from inside the attached IODEF document. The
                    Purpose and Restriction elements are often used to sort or cateogrize IODEF
                    documents, and in some use cases, determine the security and access permissions
                    of the document.</t>
                <t>When the name attribute of the category is
                    'urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:purpose', the value attribute SHOULD
                    be constrained as per section 3.2 of IODEF <xref target="RFC7970"/>, e.g.
                    traceback, mitigation, reporting, or other. </t>
                <t>When the name attribute of the category is
                    'urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:restriction', the value attribute
                    SHOULD be constrained as per section 3.2 of IODEF <xref target="RFC7970"/>, e.g.
                    public, need-to-know, private, default. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Expectation and Impact Classes" anchor="normative-expectation-impact">
                <t>It is frequently the case that an organization will need to triage their
                    investigation and response activities based upon, e.g., the state of the current
                    threat environment, or simply as a result of having limited resources. </t>
                <t> In order to enable operators to effectively prioritize their response activity,
                    it is RECOMMENDED that feed implementers provide Atom categories that correspond
                    to the IODEF Expectation and Impact classes. The availability of these feed
                    categories will enable clients to more easily retrieve and prioritize cyber
                    security information that has already been identified as having a specific
                    potential impact, or having a specific expectation. </t>
                <t> Support for these categories may also enable efficiencies for organizations that
                    already have established (or plan to establish) operational processes and
                    workflows that are based on these IODEF classes. </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
            <section title="information-type registrations" anchor="iana-it">
                <t>IANA has added the following entries to the "ROLIE Security Resource Information
                    Type Sub-Registry" registry located at <eref
                        target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/category/information-type"/>
                    . </t>
                <section title="incident information-type" anchor="iana-incident">

                    <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
                            <t>name: incident</t>
                            <t>index: TBD</t>
                            <t>reference: This document, <xref target="infotype-incident"/></t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
                <section title="indicator information-type" anchor="iana-indicator">
                    <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
                            <t>name: indicator</t>
                            <t>index: TBD</t>
                            <t>reference: This document, <xref target="infotype-indicator"/></t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="atom:category scheme registrations" anchor="iana-cat">
                <t> IANA has added the following entries to the "ROLIE URN Parameters" registry
                    located in <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rolie/"/>.</t>
                <section title="category:csirt:iodef:purpose" anchor="iana-cat-purpose">
                    <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
                            <t>name: category:csirt:iodef:purpose</t>
                            <t>Extension IRI: urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:purpose</t>
                            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="iodefcategory"/></t>
                            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
                <section title="category:csirt:iodef:restriction" anchor="iana-cat-restriction">
                    <t>The entry is as follows:<list>
                            <t>name: category:csirt:iodef:restriction</t>
                            <t>Extension IRI:
                                urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:csirt:iodef:restriction</t>
                            <t>Reference: This document, <xref target="iodefcategory"/></t>
                            <t>Subregistry: None</t>
                        </list></t>
                </section>
            </section>

        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This document implies the use of ROLIE in high-security use cases; as such, added
                care should be taken to fortify and secure ROLIE repositories and clients using this
                extension. The guidance in the ROLIE core specification is strongly recommended, and
                implementers should consider adding additional security measures as they see
                fit.</t>
            <t>When providing a private workspace for closed sharing, it is recommended that the
                ROLIE repository checks user authorization when the user sends a GET request to the
                service document. If the user is not authorized to send any requests to a given
                workspace or collection, that workspace or collection should be truncated from the
                service document in the response. In this way the existence of unauthorized content
                remains unknown to potential attackers, hopefully reducing attack surface.</t>
            <t> When sharing IODEF Version 2 documents using a ROLIE server, care should be taken to
                seperate IODEF Entries into different workspaces based on the "restriction"
                attribute of the IODEF Document (and therefore the restriction property in ROLIE).
                Security and access controls are most effectively deployed at the workspace level,
                as such, keeping private and need-to-know IODEF documents in their own workspace
                helps prevent unintended information leakage.</t>
        </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC5070; &RFC8322; &RFC4949; &RFC5023; &RFC8174;
            &RFC4287; &RFC7970; <reference anchor="stix2"
                target="https://oasis-open.github.io/cti-documentation/resources#stix-20-specification">
                <front>
                    <title>Structured Threat Information Expression 2.0</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="OASIS CTI"> Organization for the Advancement of
                            Structured Information Standards (OASIS) Cyber Threat Intelligence (CTI)
                            Technical Committee </organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2017" month="July" day="17"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>
        <references title = "Informative References"> &misp;
        </references>
        <section title="Examples of Use">
            <t>Use of this extension in a ROLIE repository will not typically change that
                repository's operation. As such, the general examples provided by the ROLIE core
                document would serve as examples. Provided below is a sample incident ROLIE entry
                containing an IODEF document: </t>
            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
  <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:rolie="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rolie-1.0">
    <id>f762c77c-057d-45c9-b805-677ab89aaf7c</id>
    <title>Sample Incident</title>
    <published>2018-09-04T18:13:51.0Z</published>
    <updated>2019-08-05T18:13:51.0Z</updated>
    <summary>A document containing an indicator of comprimise. </summary>
    <link rel="self" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/CSIRT/123456"/>
    <link rel="feed" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/CSIRT/"/>
    <rolie:property name=urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id
        value="id847201"/>
    <category
        scheme="urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type"
        term="incident"/>
    <rolie:format 
        ns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:iodef-2.0"/>
    <content type="application/xml" 
        src="http://www.example.org/rolie/csirt/123456/data"/>
  </entry>]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>Below is a sample indicator ROLIE entry containing a STIX document:</t>
            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
  <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:rolie="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rolie-1.0">
    <id>0c99df51-767f-4940-8a09-c4b607b6fe21</id>
    <title>Sample Indicator</title>
    <published>2018-09-04T18:13:51.0Z</published>
    <updated>2019-08-05T18:13:51.0Z</updated>
    <summary>A document containing an incident report. </summary>
    <link rel="self" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/CSIRT/654321"/>
    <link rel="feed" href="http://www.example.org/rolie/CSIRT/"/>
    <rolie:property name=urn:ietf:params:rolie:property:content-id
        value="exmaple:indicator:654321"/>
    <category
        scheme="urn:ietf:params:rolie:category:information-type"
        term="indicator"/>
    <rolie:format 
        ns=http://stix.mitre.org/XMLSchema/core/1.2/stix_core.xsd"/>
    <content type="application/xml" 
        src="http://www.example.org/rolie/csirt/654321/data"/>
  </entry>]]></artwork>
            </figure>
        </section>

    </back>
</rfc>
